so this is a kind of uh the second part
of the HD marov
model so uh first I will quickly review
the uh previous lecture and then moving
to the forward backward algorithm and
then finishing this lecture with BW
algorithm so the this is the hmm course
so the focus is acoustic model
right and then as I mentioned in this
lecture uh we just omit the the the uh
the condition of the pum sequence but
always remember that we have a pum
sequence just kind of omit it for the
Simplicity and we actually introduced
the four uh the the recipes to uh
formulate the EM algorithm one is the uh
introduction of the Rat variable
second one complete data likelihood
third one auxiliary function and the
fourth one parameter estimation and we
already explained it but I quickly go
through as a review of this part so
first uh introduction of relat variable
in our cases let's use the alignment
variable uh the which is having having
an information of the each time what
kind of the state we are the state
given the introduction of the Rat
variable we started to make the complete
data likelihood where we actually uh the
try to kind of starting from this uh The
Joint distribution or which we call it
complete data likelihood in the maximum
likelihood em algorithm context and then
factorizing all the kind of probability
and finally setting the probability
distribution like a gaussian and momal
distribution and so
on and by the way I explained this one
but I actually didn't explain how to get
this kind of a likelihood function which
can be obtained by marginalizing all
over the other other sequence and this
is very important and we will explain it
in the this uh lecture actually and
again you know this one has a summation
over the sequence so we cannot directly
solve it so we need some kind of a way
to solve
it and the third one it is actually the
probably the uh the the one of the most
the equation
heavy the part and I kind of providing
the a lot of equations and finally the
changing this the the the summation over
the sequence to the kind of each of the
component each of the term uh that is uh
the the pi
a the end the parameter of the gaussian
so we see almost kind of the uh uh
solving this kind of
Q function auxiliary function however we
have a kind of mysterious variable here
GMA y
us one IJ and Gamma TJ it's actually
replacing just kind of replacing this
kind of a probabilistic distribution
with these kind of variables but anyway
these kind of uh the distributions are
actually mysterious variable and I still
didn't explain how to solve it and P is
actually solved by using the forward
backward algorithm
today and then given this kind of
auxiliary function uh the last last kind
of other operation is to get the kind of
solution of the each the estimated
parameter basically based on this other
kind of objective function and then get
the Der derivative to the find the kind
of optimum uh the pi a and mu r that is
the the parameter we introduced for the
uh theing the the the concrete form of
the
the uh the
like function so this a review of the
previous uh the the estimation and then
let's focus on the what we didn't solve
so first part is as I mentioned this
posterior value stal J given
o and St minus one = I and S equal J are
the given all these two posterior
distributions are not the
solved and this the lecture we will
focus on this and actually as a
byproduct and through the kind of
forward backward algorithm we also have
a efficient way to solve this the uh the
likelihood computation so that will also
be covered in this
lecture okay so uh now we know the
Target right again the the we uh the
prepared this kind of aary function but
we don't know how to kind of providing
this one that is a target of today's
lecture okay let's go to the for
algorithm so before moving to the uh
this kind of algorithm let's try to
understand what this stal J given all
mean so this is actually the the the
using the uh the three uh the data hmm
and if we have uh five frames and so on
and then actually uh this uh the
probability can be uh regarded that we
are here for example the if tal 3 and
stal the
second the hmm state of u and then
actually this mean that we are
here okay
and then probability is that kind of our
are all possible are the passes that go
through
here so this that can be uh the the many
actually passes like for example from
here to here it goes to this passes
right and from here to here it also goes
to this pass passes in the red so the
many of the passes we have to consider
and if T becomes very LGE it's again
becomes the
exponential uh but also the note that
some of the paes are not available right
for example to go to uh to always you
know go through this
point do
we do you think this kind of a PA is
a actually not right by the way if there
is very tricky hmm like going back to
the original Pitman we usually don't use
it for the HM modeling and then it might
happens but generally the left to right
the
hmm that we do not have the exist uh
two we do not have our this pass uh that
you know satisfy that t equal three and
stal U the second hmm state so again
this is the kind of a probability of the
the second the T call some point and
then the the state is the the going to
this probability the satisfying this all
possible state but satisfying this kind
of Point okay and then the question uh
the short quiz please open to
by the way this probability is also
called occupation
probability because this means that this
occupy
here uh so uh many people actually
calling it different occupation
probability or
responsibility uh and so
on okay uh now I hope you understand
that the uh meaning of this uh
occupation
probability and then I will move to the
another kind of type of the variable
that are the uh the targetting this kind
of lecture so this one is uh the showing
that actually the previous cases the uh
it was a point right but now actually
this one showing the actually AR and
let's say the example that Tal four and
then uh the uh the for U is the the
stitching from the the second to third
state in this case actually that the uh
this becomes uh this value good C and
hmm state two and HMF state three so
this is kind of way to uh specify uh
this uh the probability
and this one is corresponding to this
red
line and then this one is corresponding
to the all possible kind of passes that
always are goes to this
one so this means that from here to
here maybe it's better to use the
pen uh from here to
here this is a kind of a possible the
the the the
trajectory and similar to the uh the
last cases there are some trajectory
that is not uh the the uh
the uh
allow to satisfy this kind of bar to
passes the this kind of arcs in this
cases this is not included uh in this
probability
the the
considerations so the the the very
similar to the last time right but the
again that it is whether the
transition or whether it is a point and
so on so let's discuss about how to
obtain these values and then to obtain
this value is actually not
straightforward uh we will introduce the
further two values uh first one is
So-Cal hard probability which is defined
by this kind of the probability and what
probability uh that is also the defined
by this kind of a probability and then
first explain why this kind of two
probability is used to form uh this
computation or this computation so the
first uh the the goal is to uh the
explain to kind of reite this equation
based on this one and this one and then
how to get this word the backward
probability is the expend dator first
Target is the again you know they make a
relationship from these two are the
equations and forward and backward
probability and probably this part is
the most complicated part in terms of
equation and among my old lectures
so first uh the Let's uh focus on this
one transition one that we you know we
have uh
discussed and we still try to use the
all kind of probabilistic rules and
first uh that we decompose two
distribution with a product rule by the
way we kind of the the uh the omit
denominator because it is not related to
the uh our Target and this means a
proportion not kind of equal but
proportional this one is proportional to
this one uh but the this kind of
denominator is not related P given Ceta
is not related to our Target so that we
eliminate it so I think this kind of a
proportional uh the notation is also
appeared in the the last week homework
so please make sure to understand this
this one this one is not equal but we
just kind of removing the
denominator or sometimes a numerator but
mostly
denominator okay so that it is still
complicated and
then we can actually uh the decompose
the the uh entire sequence to the the
subsequence which is uh we kind of used
in the last week right we just kind of
rewriting the uh entire
sequence to the
subsequences so that it is kind of easy
to the factorize the equation
data and then I actually don't want to
show you this kind of a
equation but it becomes this kind of
three component which is comes from the
the product rule and this one is
actually mostly kind of just factorizing
this first ter to this one this one and
data one it comes from here
so we have actually three uh equation
now and note that these three equations
are just product through uh nothing uh
any kind of a uh
the uh the approximation the conditional
Independence assumption was done at at
this
stage however uh that uh and I think
people here could follow it you know
it's like a you know chain right first
o1 T and then this one and this one goes
to the condition and the second this one
becomes
the um argument and then this guy
becomes the condition and the last one
this one that is argument the rest of
all our condition so it's not very
difficult but it's very
complicated but uh the I think this one
is not uh easy to solve so then that we
actually uh will uh do the condition
Independence assumption but the probably
uh the the this is difficult to make it
tractable with the conventional gausia
mixture model or conventional neural
network so that we will the conditional
Independence assumption but I think uh
that if we using the advanced NE Network
like a Transformer and so on we could
actually are the the present each of the
function so maybe one very cool research
direction would be to use the uh the
this each component to be represented by
the uh the neural network function uh
that can be a very good research topic
like combining the uh the the generative
the neural network uh into the the
classical speed sequential formulation
but yes this is possible to represent
each of the distribution by uh
the by the the neural network but the in
general if I try to kind of solve it
with the gaan mixture model or simple
new network that cannot consider the
context and so on it is very difficult
so let's use the conditional
Independence assumption for each of the
the factor and then simplify it
and this one is actually the for the not
easy uh but the I will show you the
technique to do that let's first focus
on this kind of equation and so on it's
sounds like a very complicated
observation conditioned by the one two
three four are the four variables right
and we are not sure where we kind of set
the conditional Independence assumption
and then in this cases we let's try to
use the graph the graph representation
is always easy for us to understand the
kind of
dependency so I just kind
of write the hmm basic kind of graph the
structure which are the only kind of the
depend on the observation in the
previous St these are kind of the simple
hmm graph and then let's uh pick up this
first foror
again we have a lot of kind of condition
so it sounds very complicated right but
uh let's kind of write uh the each of
the kind of uh uh the variables uh in
this kind of figure for example o one to
T is an observation and I kind of using
the yellow
circle uh in this uh the the uh figure
and then condition I use that kind of
Circle uh s = i St + 1 = J and OT + 1 O+
22t kind of setting it as a condition
and then try to think uh
whether uh these
conditions uh changes the result of this
kind of yo whether it is depend or not
so first this future
observation do you think it would depend
on this uh the previous feature in this
graph no right it's actually yeah other
models it may be but hmm there's no such
kind of passes to kind of affect this
kind previous one so we can actually
safely uh the ignore this one as an hmm
are the conditional Independence
assumptions same for for St + one
whether it's kind of the result is
change or not that doesn't kind of
affect this kind of probability
right but this one definitely yes this
one will affect this one so the uh given
this kind of a uh the graph we can
actually removing the the the some of
the
irrelevant conditions again based on the
hmm
assumption and then we can simplify that
this one is only depending on SD equal
I so basically we do the kind of the
same uh the uh the um procedure one by
one for each of the uh probability let's
now move to this one o t + 1 conditioned
on t + 2 to T subsequence
and SD = i s + 1 equal J again it is not
easy for us to understand which one is
you know
are conditionally independent and so on
right and then I would recommend you
guys to write the figure and then I
would recommend you guys to
also clarify which one is a condition
and which one is a
variable again uh the OT plus 2 to
OT they are
not uh depending on the previous feature
right hmm in general just kind of
depending on the uh the the observation
from the
state and the
second St + one this one depends on OT +
one right because this if this is J uh
if Chang it to the like for example JAL
it becom three and so on and then this
will affect this kind of variable so
this one is actually uh depend so the
question is would this
depend on
the uh ot+
one yeah some of them are are the right
answer yes it actually not do not
depend uh because already ST1 plus one
this one has some variable so regardless
of this the the previous state is
changed this one is the already as a
condition to
fix so this by the way if this is not a
lefted circle if this one is for example
without Circle and then this depends but
since this one is condition already kind
of observed signal so it will not be
changed even uh this one is changed so
actually this one only depending on
the uh St + one very
simple and the uh last one it is uh the
getting more simple so probably I can
skip uh the some uh the uh many of the
value but uh anyway from uh the OT + 2
to OT it's actually could depend on St +
one
only uh by the way again the in this
case St + one depends on st+ two because
this part is not observable so it can be
changed and then uh in this case we have
to consider the the condition of St +
one so by doing this kind of a
the careful hmm assumption applies to
the each of the
function finally this are the
complicated the three equation and we
have a last four equation but this the
three equations are actually
significantly uh
the
simplified and actually this each of the
uh the variable corresponding to for
examp example first part uh the
corresponding to the by doing some kind
of operation but then the first part is
the corresponding to the the forward
probability that I I mentioned
before and the second Factor this is
actually uh the
hmm uh sorry the gaussian uh the the the
the function that we uh introduced
before once we know the kind of state we
just have a kind of the gaan
distribution and the third factor is
represented by the uh backward
probability uh defined by the previous
equation and the uh the fourth factor is
actually State transition which is also
again we actually introduced as one of
the concrete form of this kind of
problem and so on so
uh the this uh th this kind of a uh the
state of transition probability which uh
that we introduced we first kind of
providing the interpretation of this
one this is actually the computed by the
forward probabilities backward
probability and gaussian uh and the uh
the end State transition uh probability
so by doing that uh the the problem uh
becomes how to solve this uh the uh
forward and backward probability so now
we have a relationship with this kind of
other the posterior distribution and
them and the we can do the same things
for
the uh the posterior distribution of the
occupation probability
and the
here I kind of are making the mini part
to be blank this means that it will be a
homework but note that this is the
easier than the previous one so this one
is very complicated right and the
compared with this one this derivation
is relatively easier so but it's it's
going to be still kind of a similar way
to solve the each of the equation so I
just want to make this one the other
homework so but anyway that if everyone
can follow this equation I think this is
the most complicated equation now
say and probably many of the textbook
actually didn't have this kind of a
careful explanation
uh so my lecture is quite uh the the uh
the since I couldn't understand from the
many of the textbook I spent actually
quite when I was in the your
ages I spent a lot of time to understand
this one and then the other I kind of
was providing the each solution one by
one so um I hope you guys will
understand this kind of a way of the uh
equation
yeah again some of the textbook just you
know this kind
of derivations are
written so but the I will try to kind of
give you the each of the operation one
by
one okay so
now uh the summary uh of the two
posterior probability is written as the
uh uh who are the probability Alpha uh
the backward probability
beta uh in the the gy IG cases the the
transition cases that remember this is
not the AR just AR cases and then the in
the kind of occupation cases the again
remember it is a point of the kind of a
the
probability uh this is the
represented uh by the
Alpha uh for the probability and
backward probability and some
normalization Factor both having a
normalization
factor and then the uh this state
transition and the gaan we can actually
compute some value so now it's time to
move to other comput Alpha and
beta okay okay and the first I will give
you some kind of a meaning of the
forward
probability uh so the forward
probability of this uh the case is that
the uh that we kind of generating the
observation from one to T at stal J so
let's say for example the hmm state is a
first state and the observation is one
to two and then uh the this uh the
corresponding to the uh the probability
of generating uh this point uh and the
the considering the all kind of
the uh considering all other kind of
possibility and this one is actually not
easy to
compute uh however we can actually
compute it
incrementally so
first let's uh the incrementally means
means that we can first Define the
initialization and then see that from
for example initialization Point whether
we can have some the computable or not
and if we also are the solving the
relationship between the t plus T from T
to t+ one and then we can incrementally
solve everything right so let's go to uh
this approaches and it's actually
exactly it becomes the algorithm of how
to solve this kind of value so plus
alpha 1 J so tal One cases special cases
this is a kind of the the the more like
St for we can just kind of The Institute
the substituting the the value one here
and then it actually turns out to be a
very simple uh equations of the uh the
the pi is the initial State the in the
time t uh the time one which we
introduced and the uh the uh other other
part is just a gaan so we can compute it
right
okay so this is nothing no Alpha Beta or
no Gamma orzi or other values so we can
compute this one for all kind of a
state and then let's try to kind of give
a a relationship from t plus uh T to t+
one I think this is also very
complicated and I think it's this is not
included in the homework or even in the
exam so I will quickly skip so this is
also another kind of little bit
complicated equation but I believe it is
not included in the homework so I will
just skip the
explanation uh but if you guys you know
the have time please check each of the
kind of process some rule sequence de
composition uh product rule distributive
prod uh product rule but uh the please
check this kind of a result important
part is that Alpha
T
J is represented by Alpha T minus 1 I
okay times State transition AIG J and
the goian distribution
OT so this is actually uh the
incremental equation from here to here
right so if we have you know alpha 1 and
solving Computing this one for the up to
J State you know one two three state we
computed this one right and then since
this one is incremental so we actually
know all the kind of value in the alpha
equal one and then by using the state
transition and the uh the the gaussian
distribution in the the time stamp too
we can compute Alpha to J and we can do
the kind of the same things again and
again and then it go to the kind of a
final T it's uh is a kind of end of like
the the the
computation so actually by doing that uh
we can actually compute all the the for
uh the
probability in the kind of the the the
required
equation so I will kind of make it as a
kind of a algorithm
style so first we of course have a
observation
and we know that gaussian distribution
and some uh the state transition
probability weight the AI and the
initial State
Pi so given
this first you know uh the tal one to
compute the uh this one it is
corresponding to theal one here right
and just we kind of Compu it from Old
State one to
J this is corresponding to 1 2
three and then now we have this kind of
a computation I think I also rep this
one yeah and we basically compute the
Alpha One Two Three are the three state
GES so this is a kind of the case that
there uh that we finish for the end for
uh equal line three and then from the
next uh the state H sorry next kind of
time we basically uh the Computing the
for example Alpha 21 by considering the
uh
the the state transition uh times the uh
the gaan distribution to compute this
one right and then we just kind of go
through this
computation
until
larity and I just want to mention that
this one doesn't have a summation over
the sequence right it's basically kind
of a Traverse all through the kind of a
graph at the to this point so the the
computation cost is actually maximum uh
the J Square t actually J not JT but J
Square because every time for each J we
Computing the this summation so it's
going to become the J Square so in the
other for example hmm cases it's going
to be three state or if we consider the
old character as a state it's going to
become 30 and so 30 times 30 a little
bit larger but still kind of a tractable
but the important part is linear for the
time so this one is you know that again
that we don't have to care about the
summation over the sequence and then we
can compute that this the four
probability and so
on so this is actually uh the four
probability which I believe you guys
will uh the
Implement in the for assignment too but
actually it is B right
it's or for the for yes so it's very
similar algorithm called the B algorithm
can also be kind of replacement of this
kind of algorithm and which is slightly
easier so for the the default for the
weekly not coding assignment we will ask
you guys to work on the uh the uh V
algorithm which is very similar to this
one but the the for algorithm is also
the the we prepare as a bonus point for
you and the the same for the BET
algorithm and so on this there is a kind
of a lot of uh the the note which will
be in the coding assignment and so on uh
the other note in the coding assignment
and so but I will kind of mention it
because this are quite frequent
questions
first uh this
computation is actually a lot of
multiplication
happens and the multiplication of the
the gaussian distribution
happens quite
the many times so I'm very sure that you
guys cannot solve it if we just kind of
purely are using this
equations we actually have to take the L
to compute this one but to take the log
some of the operation is not easy to
solve and then there is a log sum
exponential operation technique which is
kind of a Computing the even that we
have a kind of summation inside and we
take the log we can actually solving
this kind of a method by avoiding the
Overflow or underflow and so
which again will be described in the our
coding uh assignment document uh so for
now I just want to mention that the this
log sum exponential log domain
computation is necessary otherwise
probably you guys will always get zero
or quite large number and then you
actually cannot get kind of are the uh
the the the right value this a one note
and
another another the uh the note is that
I kind of mentioned that you know we
would kind of
check
the okay this one maybe fine we will
consider to compute the uh the the uh
the each uh the the
uh uh each uh the point that's
corresponding to the the sweeping to the
T = 2 and J = 1 to J and so
on however remember that the sum of our
operation uh would potentially have a
state transition
zero so uh like for example are
the normal Hmm this doesn't happen
right but uh usually uh what we will do
is just kind of writing this equation as
it is and then making AJ to be SP like
for example from here to here this uh
transition may not happen one two three
a one 2 three becomes zero and so on and
then we can actually uh uh comput it
efficiently or if you guys want to use
if the else and so on that is also fine
but usually people uh that are using the
SP Matrix representation for this one
and then just Computing it P is easier
but then if we take the
log of the zero of course it is not
defined right this is also another kind
of frequent question no the my equation
is exactly correct but it goes to log
zero how to deal with that um just set
the minus large number or the python
actually the prepare some
number right minus in or something like
that yeah anything is fine but just a
minus large number and then approximate
the log zero and then the program is go
well so there are lot of other ways to
avoid it but I guess this is the most
simple way so the comput it in the log
domain in this case using log sum
exponential operation and also in this
case log zero open happens and then we
just replace it minus infinity
okay so uh the now uh the now uh that we
uh the have the uh the all the for
variable and then actually there is a
kind of a very nice side effect of the
for the algorithm uh which is that we
can actually compute the the
likelihood so likelihood uh the value
here is uh defined by the uh the
PS uh the O joint
probability and then you know uh the
summation over the all the sequences
right which the last the lecture we
mentioned that we cannot compute it so
we should avoid it but actually uh the
forward computation can also providing
the this like
value so this one is actually just a
trick of making the case of if we the
reaching to the uh final
T and then uh the just kind of the rting
the original definition of the forward
variable this one is like a observation
s equal J so again we comp can compute
this value based on
the and then by us using for example Su
rule
here it actually is marginalized and it
go to
the
likelihood consider all possible State
sequence
right but this is there's no
approximation uh the we say conditional
independent assumption in the hmm is
approximation but other than that
there's no assumption let's say we use
the hmm and the computer likelihood
there's no approximation to we actually
computer likelihood by using the for the
computation so this is after the kind of
we get the all kind of the for
computation we just summing up the the
forward Val variable in the for each
state and then uh this becomes the the
likelihood and this one is also for uh
for computation it's not the
the utmost linear for the time right so
we actually can compute the like in the
linear uh the the the lineary in terms
of the time uh and so on so this is a
kind of a for the
algorithm um any questions
um I would recommend you guys again you
know this coding assignment to
to understand really about this one I
kind of explained about each of the
operation and the required equations
formulations and so on but the after you
implement something I think you guys are
further understand this kind of word the
algorithm okay so back the algorithm I
basically skip the backward the
algorithm uh the
explanation um okay this
one is missing BL blank so this means
that probably this is a the homework uh
but anyway this would be a kind of
similar to the what we are doing for the
uh for algorithm so if you carefully
check the forward algorithm computation
I hope you guys can actually derive this
kind of backward recursive backward
algorithm equations so you could see
that the result is very cool uh I think
this one yeah beta
T is comes from the t+ one so it is
actually that from the future to the uh
the the current so this are the opposite
direction to the forward so people
also called it the backward algorithm by
by the way in the backward algorithm the
initialization T is always starting from
one and the backward algorithm is
actually quite similar to the for
algorithm in terms of the
uh the uh basic form of the algorithm so
I kind of skip the explanation
but the computational cost is actually
same as the
for for algorithm and so
on
so now that's it thank you so much
for the following this kind of the
equations and so on so these are the all
of the kind of required operations so
now we have a forward algorithm and
backward algorithm so we can actually
compute this uh the the posterior
probability the transition the posterior
probability and we can also compute the
uh the uh the occupation uh probability
so these two variables are computed by
the forward backward algorithm so this
is a kind of the
entire uh the the the explanation uh of
the forward backward algorithm but I
will just have a few uh
remark so uh given this for backward
algorithm we can actually uh the uh uh
the build the parameter estimation
algorithm so remember that the EM
algorithm is actually iterative uh
iteratively performing the parameter
estimation so we have some
initialization and this parameter
estimation and then uh we can actually
compute the the uh em algorithm and so
on by the way the M step
this uh as you see that you know uh the
after the forward backward algorithm we
now know all the kind of this value gai
the gamma and so on so by doing that we
can actually compute the uh the the all
kind of parameter and so on and the uh
but the uh we can also reite this
equation by the way like this so there's
nothing so much change there but the
basically taking the
summation uh in the
beginning so this kind of the form of
taking the
summation uh the in the kind of uh the
the in the uh the uh the before the uh
getting the these Solutions are very
useful when we uh performing it
polarization uh which probably not be so
the important for many people but this
actually nature is very important uh
when we performing the polarization
because each of the kind of computing
node just kind of returning to this kind
of uh the the statistics and the master
no actually aggregating all of these
statistics and then performing this kind
of a
computation this computation and so on
so this uh the the statistics
accumulation property is actually quite
important when we kind of paralyze the
uh the the algorithm
okay so given that uh this is a kind of
a uh the last part of how to uh the
estimate the hmm other parameter
training
part first we of course we need to have
a data right and then second we actually
need to have some
initialization okay so the EM algorithm
initialization is
important and then what we will do is
first perform the forward
algorithm to compute Alpha TJ for all T
and
J it's not so difficult right we just
kind of are making it incrementally for
each time and each other
state and as a kind
of uh the side effect of the forward
algorithm after we finish the forward
algorithm we can actually also Compu
like and
like and then second part we do the kind
of backward algorithm to compute the
beta t for all T and J we just kind of
do the kind of the opposite direction of
the time and Performing the backward
probability and now we have a all set of
the alpha T and the beta T Alpha TJ and
beta
TJ and from this we can actually compute
the uh this gamma Z which is the
probability of the occupation or
probability of the transition right from
uh this one and this one from this one
and the parameters we also can compute
this
one now we know that all kind of a time
and all kind of state or all kind of a
transition these are the
values and then given these kind of
values we are the computer sufficient
statistics and then we update the AGM
parameter in this Cas is pi a mu R is
updated this are one
iteration after that using it as a kind
of a new parameter and then doing the
forward backward computer gamma ZT and
the suff sufficient statistics at the
computation and do the kind of a hmm
parameter update
again and then where we kind of use the
likelihood likelihood is used to monitor
whether this kind of a the value uh is
uh the the uh the correctly uh the uh
estimated or not if this likelihood
value goes down which means that your
algorithm is wrong and we usually using
this likelihood as a the
convergence conditions for example if
the likelihood value uh becomes
converted gradually which we usually
observe and then if the the likelihood
doesn't kind of improve so so much with
some kind of threshold we can actually
cut the uh the uh this
other iterations and then we can
actually update the result but as I
mentioned in the last uh Thea in the the
last week so this is actually em
algorithm is okay to the land many times
uh is would not uh degrade the
performance in terms of the like Hood
criteria which is not very bad uh so you
guys can you know do uh this kind of
iteration many times but again to save
the kind of a the computation people
usually check the likelihood and then
once it is converted we just cut
it okay so that's the kind of our end of
the this hmm part now there are all
computations are tractable so
there are the summation over the
sequence everywhere right but it was
gone for all the kind of computation and
then we can actually make it and then
this is iterative computation similar to
The Back propagation and initialization
is very important but with that we can
actually add they get kind of very good
other
convergence oh I also have to mention
this there is no high parameter like a
learning rate B size and so on right we
don't have to use it so this is actually
nice part of the uh the the EM algorithm
uh but the initialization is very
sensitive so uh in
the uh
our uh the coding
assignment uh this is also another
second and frequent questions uh the how
to initialize it it's clearly mentioned
in the our kind of write but how to
initialize it we will basically
performing The
Uniform assignment for the hmm
cases this is not very bad as
initialization and the gaan mixture
cases we use the K me and this is part
of the
assignment okay so that's it uh in this
lecture and any
questions okay uh thank you so much